Guide to the Thomas Dixon Jr. Papers, 1880s-1959 RL.11865
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas Dixon Jr. Papers
1880s-1959
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dixon, Thomas, Jr, 1864-1946
RL.11865
3.0 Linear Feet 4 gray hollinger boxes, 1 oversize folder, and 1 separately boxed volume.
Thomas Dixon Jr. (1864-1946) was a white supremacist, novelist, playwright, and clergyman, originally from North Carolina. Dixon authored The Leopard's Spots (1902) and The Clansman (1905), which later was adapted into D. W. Griffith's film The Birth of a Nation (1915). This collection contains literary drafts of his plays and novels, some correspondence, and other legal materials and photographs.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged by formats: writings, correspondence, legal papers, photographs, and other materials.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Dixon Jr. was a white supremacist, novelist, playwright, lawyer, and clergyman (1864-1946). Dixon authored The Leopard's Spots: A Romance of the White Man's Burden (1902) and The Clansman: A Historical Romance of the Ku Klux Klan (1905), the latter of which was adapted into a play and the 1915 D.W. Griffith film The Birth of a Nation.
Dixon was born in Shelby, N.C., and attended Wake Forest College and Johns Hopkins University (where he befriended Woodrow Wilson). He graduated from Greensboro Law School in 1885, and briefly served in the North Carolina General Assembly as a Democrat. He was ordained as a Baptist minister in 1886, and held appointments in Raleigh, Boston, and New York City. He left preaching in the late 1890s to become a lecturer on the Chautauqua circuit. He later became a novelist and playwright, seeking to tell the "true story" of Southern Reconstruction. His works glorified slavery and white supremacy, celebrated the Ku Klux Klan, and opposed miscengenation, socialism, and female suffrage.
Although his success as an author, playwright, and lecturer led to extreme wealth and popularity, Dixon lost much of his fortune to stock market crashes in the early 1900s, and to a land speculation venture called "Wildacres Retreat" which he attempted to fund in western North Carolina in the late 1920s. He was partially paralyzed following a cerebral hemorrhage in 1939, and suffered poor health for the remainder of his life.
He married his first wife, Harriet Dixon, in 1886, and the couple had three children: Thomas III, Louise, and Gordon. Following Harriet's death in 1937, Dixon married actress Madelyn Clare Donovan in 1939. She died in Raleigh, N.C., in 1975.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Thomas Dixon Jr. were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in different accessions. The earliest acquisition was a 1959 purchase of the manuscript volumes "The Sins of the Father" and "The Sun Virgin" from the Swann Galleries in New York City. The bulk of the papers were purchased in 1960 from a Mr. B. L. Alexander, in Raleigh. Fragmentary letters and clippings were added in the 1970s. All of these purchases were funded through the Flowers endowment.
Collection Overview
Collection contains literary manuscript drafts, correspondence, family photographs, and printed materials and clippings. The bulk of the collection consists of Dixon's holograph and typescript drafts of scripts, novels, and corrections for titles he authored including The Clansman, The Birth of a Nation (includes draft play script and film's shot list), The One Woman (bound page proof), the Love Complex, God's Fool: A Drama of Negro Life in Modern Harlem, Shanghai Express, The Great American, The Man in Gray, A Man of the People: A Drama of Abraham Lincoln, The Sins of the Father (2 bound volumes, holograph drafts), The Sun Virgin (bound volume, holograph draft), and The Flaming Sword. The bulk of these works depict romanticized, racist, Lost Cause morality plays, with Dixon's texts advocating white supremacy, segregation, violence against Black people, misogyny (and opposing women's suffrage), and miscengeny. There are also some drafts by other writers, including Majorie Chase, W. Ward Marsh, and Ernest De Journo. Correspondence and legal papers in this collection tend to relate to his publications, including contracts and copyrights; includes a letter from Jerome Dowd reflecting on the Tulsa Race Riot. There are also some legal proceedings from a 1920s court case between Dixon (defendent) and the National Drama Corporation, and some letters discussing Dixon's poor health. The collection includes some materials relating to Dixon's involvement with the Mount Mitchell Association, a land development company in Western North Carolina; materials on spirituality from Dixon's widow, Madelyn Donovan Dixon; family photographs and portraits of Dixon, his first wife (Harriet Dixon), his second wife (Madelyn Donovan Dixon), and some of his children and other relatives, at times unidentified; and assorted printed materials, flyers, notes, and unidentified drafts.
Racism -- United States; Authors, American -- 20th century -- United States; Authors and publishers -- United States -- Correspondence; North Carolina -- History; Race discrimination -- United States; Whites -- Race identity -- United States; White supremacy movements -- United States; Hate Speech -- United States; American fiction; Misogyny in literature; Miscegenation in literature; Stereotypes (Social psychology) in literature; Griffith, D. W. (David Wark), 1875-1948; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Dixon, Harriet; Dixon, Madelyn Donovan; Mount Mitchell Association of Arts and Sciences; Ku Klux Klan (19th cent.)
- Autobiography fragments, 1940s (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  (Approx. 5 pages of family history, with Lost Cause perspective.)
- The Birth of a Nation silent film shot list, by Thomas Dixon(?) Author unidentified, Approximately 1915 (Box 1)
  Approx. 35 pages typescript. By reel - contains scene summary and caption text.
- The Birth of a Nation: A Play in Prologue and 4 Acts, by Thomas Dixon, 1935 (Box 1)
  Typescript pages (appears complete).
- The Clansman: Fall of the Master. First sketch revised, by Thomas Dixon, 1910s-1920s?; 2 folders (Box 1)
  Typescript script pages, repaired and sewn together; original pages in poor and worn condition. Some pages have stamped "Alice Kauser: 1432 Broadway, New York." Folder contains introductory pages (title page, contents page "The Clansman: An American Drama in Four Acts, from his two novels 'The Leopard's Spots' and the 'Clansman.'" and then script pages of Act 1: The Fall of the Master, and a character list. (Includes Folder 2, with photocopy.)
- The Clansman, Acts 1-4, by Thomas Dixon, 1910s-1920s?; 2 folders (Box 1)
  Typescript play script draft pages, with corrections. Stamped with Alice Kauser: 1402 Broadway, New York. (Includes Folder 2, with photocopy)
- The Flaming Sword loose fragments, by Thomas Dixon, 1938? (Box 1)
  Typescript and manuscript draft pages, edits; some notes.
- The Flaming Sword: press and promotional materials, 1939 (Box 1)
- God's Fool: A Drama of Negro Life in Modern Harlem, script by Thomas Dixon, unknown (Box 1)
  Typescript draft pages of a script. Pages are summaries, not script lines. Characters are racist caricatures in a morality play. "Theme: the conflict between the old ideals of Religion, Truth, Right and Honor and the Modern Jazz Worship of the World, the Flesh and the Devil - illustrated in the clash between the Old and New Negro in Harlem…." Many pages torn, worn, water-stained.
- The Great American, script by Thomas Dixon, Approximately 1920 (Box 1)
  Typescript play script pages, previously repaired. Approx. 1920. Romanticized racist historical romance, set in Mississippi in 1918.
- Lincoln Triumphant: The Story of an American Boy, script by Thomas Dixon, 1920? (Box 1)
  Typescript play script pages, prologue only, undated. 7 p. "Founded on his novel The Southerner." Set in Indiana, 1820.
- The Love Complex: A Drama of Impulse, script by Thomas Dixon, 1925? (Box 1)
  Typescript play "founded on Mr. Dixon's novel of the same title." Previously repaired, appears complete.
- The Man in Gray: A Drama of the Life of Lee. Play in 4 Acts (24 scenes), by Thomas Dixon, 1922? (Box 1)
  Typescript play script "founded on his novel of the same title, 1922". Bound, 88 p.
- A Man of the People: A Drama of Abraham Lincoln, script by Thomas Dixon, 1920? (Box 2)
  Typescript draft pages, with corrections. 107 p.
- The One Woman, bound volume, by Thomas Dixon, 1903?; 1 Volumes 1 boxed volume (Volume 1)
  Cloth boards, printed and bound (loose spine) page proof, 350 p. Acquired, cataloged 1969. Originally numbered as M-6001.
- Shanghai Express, by Thomas Dixon, 1930s? (Box 2)
  Typescript synopsis, 22 p. Romanticized racist historical romance, set in China (on a train and in the countryside).
- The Sins of the Father (part 1 and 2), novel by Thomas Dixon, 1912?; 2 Volumes (Box 2)
  Cloth boards, holograph manuscript drafts. Cataloged 1959. Originally L-6369 and 6370. "A Romance of the South," a racist historical novel denouncing miscegenation between Southern whites and Blacks.
- The Sun Virgin, novel by Thomas Dixon, 1929? (Box 3)
  Incan-themed racist historical romance novel about Francisco Pizaro. Holograph manuscript draft, with corrections and edits, bound in cloth boards, 434 p.
- The Vision: An Epic of America, synopsis by Thomas Dixon, 1940s? (Box 3)
  36 p. Typescript synopsis "tentative outline". Romanticized historical saga, set in Washington D.C. between 1914 and 1940.
- Unidentified typescript pages (perhaps alternative version of The One Woman play), by Thomas Dixon(?), 1918? (Box 3)
  Characters Ruth, Kate, and George (The Professor).
- Chase, Majorie. The Reckoning: A Play in a Prologue and Three Acts, 1920 (Box 3)
  Play set in New York and Colorado; character Mary "a woman who can be strong yet a woman through and through." Condition poor, with scotch tape repairs to damaged pages.
- De Journo, Ernest, with Thomas Dixon: A Slave of Love, 1930s? (Box 3)
  Love story set in Renaissance Persia.
- Marsh, W. Ward: The Loneliest Woman: A Play in Five Scenes, 1928 (Box 3)
  Typescript draft script. Previously repaired. Love story set in middle America.
- Woolfolk, L. B.: Great Red Dragon, or London Money Power, 1889-1890 (Box 3)
  Typescript draft pages, with racist and antisemetic conspiracy theories regarding "Money Power", a force within economic and political power structures responsible for the financial crash of 1873. Ex: "The Money Kings keep a partnership with their gentile agents; in the next era, they will kick out the gentiles and put the business in the hands of their countrymen, the Jews."
- Correspondence, 1928-1940 (Box 3)
  Incoming letters to Dixon regarding copyright, publication, distribution of his books by various publishers; other correspondence regarding the Mount Mitchell Association and his Western North Carolina real estate ventures in the late 1920s. Includes a letter from Jerome Dowd to Dixon (1938) reflecting on the 1921 Tulsa race riot and massacre of African Americans. This appears connected to Dixon's research and writing of The Flaming Sword, published 1939.
- Correspondence, 1940-1959 (Box 3)
  Includes incoming letters to Dixon, including fan mail for The Leopard's Spots. Correspondence regarding The Flaming Sword publication and publicity with The Monarch Publishing Company (1940), and printing costs owed to Kingsport Press Inc. Also contains correspondence to Madelyn (Clare) Donovan Dixon from her family, at times regarding Thomas's poor health. Following Thomas Dixon's death (1946), correspondence includes memorial cards, letters to Madelyn congratulating her on an appointment as Federal Court clerk, and letters regarding the settlement of Thomas Dixon's estate.
- Loose pages of manuscript notes, 1930s-1940s? (Box 4)
- Loose printed materials and clippings, 1920s-1940s (Box 4)
- The Asheville Advocate's Western N.C. Development Edition: "Thomas Dixon Creating National Institution in W.N.C.", 1926 June 4; 1 folders 1 oversize folder (Oversize-folder 1)
  Oversize newspaper regarding the real estate development program in Mount Mitchell area, 8p. (fragile, brittle)
- Scattered reviews and blurbs of Dixon's works, and biographical newspaper clippings, 1930s (Box 4)
  Contains some Dixon biographical clippings from the 1970s acquired as reference/resources (not originally part of this collection).
- Photographs of Dixon and his family, 1880s-1940s (Box 4)
  Snapshots and portraits of Thomas Dixon, wife Harriet Dixon, their children; and wife Madelyn Clare Donovan Dixon (including as actress). Several photographs have captions with family names; others are unidentified homes or people.
- Madelyn Donovan Dixon syllabus about occultism, 1940s (Box 4)
- Assorted financial papers and receipts, 1910s-1930s (Box 4)
- Legal materials, 1910s-1930s (Box 4)
  Including various literary manuscript contracts, agreements, copyrights, and licenses for Dixon's writings
- Supreme Court Appellate Division: First Department. Thorne Baker (Trustee in Bankruptcy of National Drama Corporation), plaintiff-appellant, against Thomas Dixon, defendant-respondent, 1923 (Box 4)
  Bound volume, 749 p. Binding and first page damaged.